<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony to the fulfilling the promise of God relating to such women who through the pouring out of Gods Spirit upon them are become prophetesses, daughters, and handmaidens and their prophecying, teaching, preaching,and praying through the operation of the Spirit of Christ, in the church proved lawfully by several plain Scripture testimonies and examples, out of both the Old and New Testaments, both under the time of the Law and also in the Gospel despensation, and the common objection alleged against the same from the Apostle Pauls words in I Cor. 14, 34 and I Tim. 2, 12 &amp;c. clearly answered : recommended to the consciences of all that value the testimony of Holy Scripture / by one who hath diligently searched the Scripture, and hath had an high esteem thereof from his youth, Thomas Camm.</title>
            <author>Camm, Thomas, 1641-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32902</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C396A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5431</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13687282</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13687282</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101359</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32902)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101359)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 841:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony to the fulfilling the promise of God relating to such women who through the pouring out of Gods Spirit upon them are become prophetesses, daughters, and handmaidens and their prophecying, teaching, preaching,and praying through the operation of the Spirit of Christ, in the church proved lawfully by several plain Scripture testimonies and examples, out of both the Old and New Testaments, both under the time of the Law and also in the Gospel despensation, and the common objection alleged against the same from the Apostle Pauls words in I Cor. 14, 34 and I Tim. 2, 12 &amp;c. clearly answered : recommended to the consciences of all that value the testimony of Holy Scripture / by one who hath diligently searched the Scripture, and hath had an high esteem thereof from his youth, Thomas Camm.</title>
                  <author>Camm, Thomas, 1641-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andrew Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Witness bearing (Christianity) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101359:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY TO The fulfilling the <hi>Promiſe</hi> of God, relating To ſuch WOMEN WHO Through the pouring out of Gods Spirit upon them, are become Propheteſſes, Daughters and Handmaidens: And their Prophecying, Teaching, Preaching and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through the Operation of the Spirit of Chriſt, in the Church proved lawfully, by ſeveral plain Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Teſtimonies and Examples, out of both the old and new Teſtaments, both under the time of the Law, and alſo in the Goſpel Deſpenſation. And the common Objection alledged againſt the ſame, from the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> words, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> clearly anſwered.</p>
            <p>Recommended to the Conſciences of all that value the Teſtimony of holy Scripture, by one who hath diligently ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Scripture, and hath had an high eſteem thereof from his youth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Camm.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>This is that which is ſpoken by the Prophet</hi> Joel, And it ſhall come to paſs in the latter day ſaith <hi>God, I</hi> will pour out of my <hi>Spirit</hi> upon all Fleſh, and your <hi>Sons</hi> and your <hi>Daughters</hi> ſhall, <hi>Propheſie,</hi> your young <hi>Men</hi> ſhall ſee <hi>Viſions,</hi> and your old <hi>Men</hi> ſhall dream <hi>Dreams:</hi> And on my <hi>Servants</hi> and on my <hi>Hand-maidens I</hi> will pour out in thoſe days of my <hi>Spirit,</hi> and they ſhall <hi>Propheſie,</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts 2.</hi>
               </bibl> — Follow after Charity, deſire ſpiritual Gifts, but rather that you may <hi>Propheſie,</hi> for you may all <hi>Propheſie</hi> one by one, that all may learn, and all may be edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Cor. 14.</hi>
               </bibl> — For as many of you as have been <hi>Baptized</hi> into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt, there is neither <hi>Jew</hi> nor <hi>Greek,</hi> there is neither <hi>Bond</hi> nor <hi>Free,</hi> there is neither <hi>Male</hi> nor <hi>Female,</hi> for you are all one in Chriſt,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 3.27, 28.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Andrew Sowle:</hi> And ſold at the <hi>three Kyes</hi> in <hi>Nags-head-Court</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:101359:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101359:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE To the Reader.</head>
            <p>NOtwithſtanding that ſeveral have written upon the ſame Subject, and that both plain, clear and weighty, as the Lord by his bleſſed Spirit hath moved and aſſiſted you, yet was I under obligation to caſt in my Mite amongſt my Brethren, that by many Witneſſes the matter may be Eſtabliſhed) in Teſtimony to the fulfilling that bleſſed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Almighty God, in pouring out of his Spirit upon both <hi>Daughters</hi> and <hi>Handmaidens,</hi> as well as <hi>Sons</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> and their Prophecying to Edification in the <hi>Church;</hi> and the more eſpecially becauſe the following Teſtimony hath been a weighty concern upon my mind, for ſeveral days, in the movings and openings of the holy Spirit: And now in the tender B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wels of Love ſincerely as a Chriſtians Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Service, Recommends the ſame to the Conſciences of all ſort of People that profeſs Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Yet more particularly; And <hi>firſt,</hi> unto ſuch as have taken occaſion to render and conclude thoſe People called <hi>Quakers</hi> to be deluded, and ſleighters, undervaluers and den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers of the <hi>holy Scriptures,</hi> only becauſe <hi>Daughters</hi> and <hi>Handmai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,</hi> through the operation of Gods holy <hi>Spirit,</hi> in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine movings thereof, do in their Meetings and Gatherings together, Speak and Propheſie as the Spirit gives utterance, that the gain-ſaying Reflections and common Objections of ſuch may be repelled and fully anſwered.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101359:3"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That all ſuch as are well ſatisfied in the aforeſaid Practice of Womens Speaking and Prophecying in the Gatherings of Gods People, which is his Church and Congregation, may be furniſhed with Scripture Teſtimonies and Examples, to anſwer the Objections of all Gain-ſayers.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> For the information and help of ſuch as may through a kind of reſpect, to (at leaſt the Letter of) holy Scripture, yet being but little or rather unacquainted with the holy Spirit, that opens the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery therein, doth either read them in too literal a Sence, or elſe through Ignorance wreſt them, and therefore may ſcruple or doubt of the Fractice of Gods People in this particular; now if thou <hi>Reader</hi> be ſuch a one, I tenderly beg of thee to wait low in thy Mind, to feel the Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the holy Spirit, by which holy Scripture was given forth, whereby thou mayſt not only have the myſtery thereof opened in thee, but alſo receive benefit by what hereafter (in this following Treatiſe) out of holy Scripture, is in the Love of God recommended to thee in order to thy Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>I have only made uſe of Scripture Teſtimony and Examples, as through the holy Spirit that good Remembrancer they were brought into thy mind, yet I believe much might be added, not only from holy Writ, but alſo from the Practice of many Godly Women, in the dawning of the Goſpel-Day, and beginning of Reformation in theſe latter Ages, when the Superſtition of <hi>Popery</hi> began to be diſcovered and proteſted againſt, who through the Spirit were made Inſtrumental in the Hand of God, for the building up and confirming others in their Meeting and Congregating together, as by Hyſtory of credit amongſt <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> may more fully be demonſtrated, but at preſent omitted for Brevity ſake, wherefore read and receive the following Lines in true and ſincere Love to the Truth as it is in <hi>Jeſus,</hi> abandoning all Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, that the benefit deſigned thou mayſt reap to Gods Glory, Truth's Praiſe, and thy own Satisfaction and Comfort, wherein my end will be fully anſwered, who is one that heartily wiſheth to thee, and all Men, the knowledge of the Truth as it is in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> to whom with God the Father be Glory and Praiſe in all his Churches, World without end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Camm.</signed> 
               <dateline>Camſgil, <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 10th <hi>Month 1684.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101359:3"/>
            <head>A TESTIMONY TO The fulfilling of the <hi>Promiſe</hi> of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AND firſt in the time of the Law, you may read in <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. that <hi>Miriam, Moſes</hi>'s Siſter, was a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, and propheſied in the Church or Congregation, for the Word Church is by worthy <hi>Tindal</hi> moſt frequently Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Congregation: And in <hi>Num.</hi> 11.29. you may read how <hi>Moſes</hi> the Man of God, who had the Spirit of God, and knew the Mind of God, wiſhed that all the Lords People, (Mark, all the Lords People) both Sons and Daughters, did Propheſie or were Prophets: Again you may read in the 4th and 5th <hi>Chapters</hi> of <hi>Judges,</hi> how <hi>Deborah</hi> that Judged <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and was a Mother in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> through the Spirit of Chriſt, Propheſied and Praiſed the Lord amongſt the People, the Congregation or Army to whom the Lord had given a great Victory over their Enemies; further it may be obſerved, that <hi>Deborah</hi> was a Mother in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and its the concern of Mothers to Inſtruct and Teach their Children, yea all others over whom God hath made them Judges and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers.</p>
            <p>Again in the 1ſt. and 2d. <hi>Chap.</hi> of 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> you may read how <hi>Hanah</hi> Pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to, and Praiſed the Lord, and rejoyed in Gods Salvation, in many gracious Expreſſions; yea, and in the Temple, and in the preſence of the High Prieſt <hi>Eli,</hi> and we read not that he for bad her: And in 2 <hi>King</hi> 22. you may read how good <hi>Joſiah</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> ſent to <hi>Huſdab</hi> the Propheteſs to enquire of the Lord by her, and not by any other Prophet: And you may alſo read what a bleſſed effect her Words had upon both King, High-prieſt and People, to a great Reformation: Moreover in <hi>Luke</hi> 2. you may read how, that at the time, that the Child <hi>Jeſus</hi> was by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101359:4"/>the Parents brought into the Temple, to do to him after the Cuſtom of the Law: There was one <hi>Anna</hi> a Propheteſs, a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of about Fourſcore and Four Years old, who departed not from the Temple, but ſerved God with Faſting and Praying day and night; and in that inſtant (with good old <hi>Simeon</hi>) gave thanks likewiſe unto the Lord, and ſpoke of <hi>Jeſus</hi> there, in the Temple (Mark in the Temple) to the Church or Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there) yea to all them that looked for Redemption in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem;</hi> now obſerve ſhe was a Propheteſs and departed not from the Temple, then where did ſhe Propheſie but in the Temple, Pray in the Temple, gave Thanks in the Temple, and ſpake of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in the Temple to all that looked for Redemption in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael?</hi> And we read not that any of the Prieſts or Miniſters of the Temple did forbid Her, neither good old <hi>Simeon</hi> that was filled with the Holy Ghoſt, and came by the Spirit into the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and knew the Mind of God, he did not forbid Her to Speak or Pray, or Propheſie in the Temple, the Church or Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; no they joyned and was at unity in their Teſtimony, in that bleſſed Spirit by whom both their Mouths were opened to ſpeak in Prayer and Prophecying to Gods Glory, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Edification of all that looked for Redemption by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Further you may read in <hi>Luke</hi> 1. how <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> was filled with the Holy Ghoſt, and did Propheſie, and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> bleſſedly magnified the Lord; what gracious Words proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from them through the operation of the holy Spirit that's one in Male and Female: Again in <hi>John.</hi> 4. it may be read how the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> that diſcourſed with Chriſt at <hi>Jacob</hi>'s <hi>Well,</hi> went into the City <hi>Syehar,</hi> and Preached <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the Men therein, and what an effectual Sermon it was, though but ſhort, Come ſaid ſhe, <hi>See a Man that hath told me all that ever I did, Is not this the Chriſt?</hi> and many of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> of that City, believed on him, for the Saying of the Woman which teſtified, <hi>He told me all that ever I did;</hi> now by whats above-ſaid, its plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evinced, that God in the time of the Law poured out of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit upon <hi>Daughters</hi> and <hi>Handmaiden,</hi> as well as upon <hi>Sons</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> and they Propheſied, Preached and Taught, yea and Prayed too, and Praiſed the Everlaſting God in the Church or Congregation, in the Temple, and in the prefence of the High-prieſts and other Miniſters of the Temple, and we read not that they were for bidden.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101359:4"/>
            <p> But it may be Objected, <hi>This was in the time of the Law, but now the Goſpel time is come, and hath not</hi> Paul, <hi>that was a Miniſter of the Goſpel, prohibited Womens Speaking in the Church,</hi> in 1 Cor. 14.34. &amp; 1 Tim. 2.12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is anſwered, that by whats above written its mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, how God did pour out of his Spirit upon ſome Women, Daughters and Handmaidens according to meaſure in the time of the Law, and they Preached or Propheſied, and Taught in the Church or Congregation, and Praiſed and magnified God there alſo, through the operation of the Spirit then poured out upon them, though but in the time of the Law, which was to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled and come to an end (mark that) And then God promiſed, that cannot lie, to pour out of his Spirit more univerſally upon all Fleſh, as may be read in <hi>Joel</hi> 2. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, that I will pour out of my Spirit upon all Fleſh, and your Sons and your Daughters,</hi> (mark, Daughters alſo) <hi>ſhall Propheſie; your old Men ſhall dream Dreams, your young Men ſhall ſee Viſions, and alſo upon the Servants and upon the Handmaids</hi> (mark Handmaids alſo) <hi>in thoſe days will I pour out my Spirit:</hi> O bleſſed Promiſe to be fulfilled in the latter Days, the Goſpel Days; yea, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Peter</hi> bears Record to the fulfilling thereof, as may be read in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>This is that,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>which is ſpoken by the Prophet</hi> Joel, <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in the latter Days ſaith God, I will pour out of my Spirit upon all Fleſh, and your Sons and your Daughters ſhall Propheſie, and your young Men ſhall ſee Viſions, and your old Men ſhall dream Dreams, and on my Servants, and on my Handmaidens, I will pour out in thoſe days of my Spirit, and they ſhall Propheſie;</hi> mark, God ſaith they ſhall Propheſie, here is the time of the fulfilling of the Promiſe, this is the Goſpel Day, wherein Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Handmaidens is to Propheſie more univerſally then in the time of the Law, though then God poured out of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit upon ſome, and they Propheſied as before ſaid: This is ſo glorious a Diſpenſation, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>You may all</hi> (mark all) <hi>Propheſie one by one,</hi> yea, he adviſeth all to follow after Charity, and deſire after ſpiritual Gifts, <hi>But rather,</hi> ſaith he (mark that) <hi>that you may Propheſie, for he that Propheſieth ſpeaketh unto Men to Edification and Exhortation, and Comfort, yea, he that Propheſieth, Edifieth the Church,</hi> 1 Cor. 14. Now that the Church might be thus Edified, hath God Almighty in his infinite Kindneſs, in this latter Day, and Goſpel Day, poured
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101359:5"/>out of his Spirit upon both Sons and Daughters, and they may both Propheſie in the Church or Congregation; yea, God thats above all hath ſaid, <hi>they ſhall Propheſie,</hi> who therefore can limit the Spirit of the Almighty, who can ſet bounds thereto, its one and the ſame in the Female as the Male, and is through both to ſpeak, yea, for all in this Church of God, that hath the Spirit of God poured upon them, may by the ſame Propheſie to Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>For you may all</hi> (mark all) <hi>Propheſie one by one, that all may Learn, and all may be Comforted,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 14.31. For its not the Woman that ſpeaks, but the Spirit of the Father through the Male and Female, according to Chriſt's Saying in <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Its not you,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>that ſpeakes, but the Spirit of the Father that ſpeaketh in you:</hi> Now its not the Man nor the Woman that ſpeaketh, but the Spirit that God the Father hath poured upon Sons and Daughters, Servants and Handmaids in this Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Day, that Holy Day and Sabboth, teſtified of in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13. as followeth thus, <hi>viz. If thou turn away thy foot from the Sabboth, from doing thy Pleaſure on my Holy Day, and call the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both a Delight, the Holy of the Lord, Honourable, and ſhalt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him, not doing thine own Ways, nor finding thine own Pleaſure, nor Speaking</hi> (obſerve nor Speaking) <hi>thine own Words;</hi> here nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man nor Woman is to ſpeak their own Words, for every Woman or Man either that ſpeaks their own Words, are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to ſpeak in the Church, in the Congregation, in the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Aſſemblies of Gods People, for ſuch regard not the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sabboth, the Goſpel-Day, and Holy, in which Male nor Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male are to ſpeak their own Words, for who are Baptized into the one Spirit, who have drunk into the one Spirit, who have put on the Lord Chriſt, is a new Creature, as ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Therefore if any Man be in Chriſt, he is a new Creature, old things are paſt away, behold all things are become new;</hi> here is the bleſſed Reſtoration out of the Fall, through Chriſt thats one in both Male and Female, both hath he purchaſed by an high price unto himſelf; and ſuch are not to ſpeak their own Words in his Church, in this Goſpel day and time of his holy Sabboth, but to adminſter out of the Abundance of the Spirit, that God the Father gives; here the Spirit utters it ſelf through the Male and Female, for both are one in the Spirit of Truth, both are one in Chriſt as may be read in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27, 28. <hi>For as many of you as have been Baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt, there is neither</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101359:5"/>Jew <hi>nor</hi> Greek, <hi>there is neither Bond nor Free, there is neither Male nor Female, for they are all one in Chriſt;</hi> Here is no difference in Chriſt, Chriſt may ſpeak in Male and in Female, who is it that will limit him in his Church, may not he ſpeak through the Daughters and Handmaidens that's filled with his Spirit, as well as through the Sons and Servants being there is no difference, all are one in him? yea, he doth and hath done it in his Church and Congregation, who is Lord and Law-giver, and is to be Obeyed, Worſhipped and Served both by Male and Female. So its clear that its not the Woman that's filled with the Spirit, in whom Chriſt dwells, rules, and is Head that's forbidden, or not permitted to ſpeak in the Church; but ſuch as are ſilly Women that are ever learning, but never come to the knowledge of Chriſt the Truth, that's not taught by him, nor led by him, ſuch as obey him not; ſo uſurps an Authority, ſpeaks their own Words, ſpeaks of themſelves, not from Chriſt, not out of the aboundance of the Spirit that God gives, but out of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of their own unſanctified Hearts and Wiſdom, ſuch, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men or Women, are forbidden to ſpeak in the Church, in the Congregation they are to be ſilent, and to learn in Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, its a ſhame for ſuch to uſurp Authority and ſpeak. Now by whats before ſaid its cleared that the Spirit is poured out upon Sons and Daughters alſo, and they are to propheſie; let's ſee what Teſtimonies the holy Scriptures affords, as with reſpect to Practice, ſince the time of the Goſpel revealed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> was commiſſioned to Peach and Publiſh the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt to his Diſciples, as may be read in <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.7. where ſhe was commanded to go quickly and tell his Diſciples, <hi>That he is riſen from the Dead, and behold he goeth before you into</hi> Galilee, <hi>there ſhall you ſee him, lo, I have told you.</hi> And in <hi>Mark</hi> 16.7, 9, 10. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Salom</hi> were commanded to publiſh unto the Diſciples the Reſurrection of Chriſt, where its ſaid, <hi>Go your way, tell his Diſciples, and</hi> Peter, <hi>that he goeth before you into</hi> Galilee, <hi>there ſhall you ſee him, as he ſaid unto you.</hi> Here you may ſee that theſe good Women were commiſſioned by the Angel to preach the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt to his Diſciples: Furthermore, when Jeſus was riſen early the firſt day of the Week, he appeared firſt to <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> out of whom he had caſt ſeven Devils, and ſhe went and told them that ſhe had been with him, as they mourned and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101359:6"/>wept. And in <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.9, 10. <hi>And returned from the Sepulchre, and told all theſe things unto the Eleven, and to all the reſt</hi> (mark, all the reſt) <hi>it was</hi> Mary Magdalen, <hi>and</hi> Joana, <hi>and</hi> Mary <hi>the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of</hi> James, <hi>and other Women</hi> (Mark, other Women alſo) <hi>that were with them, which told theſe things unto the Apoſtles.</hi> Again, in <hi>John</hi> 20.16, 17, 18. <hi>Jeſus ſaith unto her,</hi> Mary, <hi>ſhe turneth her ſelf, and ſaith unto him,</hi> Rabboni, <hi>which is to ſay,</hi> Maſter. <hi>Jeſus ſaith unto her, Touch me not, for I am not yet aſcended to my Father, but go to my Brethren, and ſay to them,</hi> (obſerve) and ſay to them, <hi>I aſcend unto my Father, and your Father, and to my God, and your God.</hi> Mary Magdalen <hi>came and told the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that ſhe had ſeen the Lord, and that he had ſpoken theſe things unto her.</hi> Hereby its clear that <hi>Mary</hi> was the firſt unto whom Jeſus appeared after he was riſen, and the firſt Preacher of his Reſurrection; ſhe and the other Women, before mentioned, ſpoke of and publiſhed the Reſurrection of Jeſus unto the eleven, and all the reſt. Surely none will deny but the eleven and all the reſt was the Church of Chriſt in that day; in this Church they ſpoke, preached and taught, and was commiſſioned thereto by the Lord, Chriſt, the Head of the Church, the everlaſting High-Prieſt, whoſe Lips preſerve true Knowledge, whom all are to hear and obey, and whoever doth not hear the voice of this Prophet, is to be cut off from amongſt the People, is to be ſeparated from his Church, and not to ſpeak therein, for its whom he Commiſſions, whom he dictates to, and ſpeaks in, whether Male or Female, that is to Speak, Preach and Teach good things to Edification, in his Church, in the Congregations and Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his People. Further, <hi>Aquilla,</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla</hi> his Wife, were both Expounders of the Way of God more perfectly, as may be read in <hi>Acts</hi> 18. verſ. 27. Them doth <hi>Paul</hi> greet by Name in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> Chap. 16. and there calls them both his Helpers in Chriſt Jeſus: To whom not only <hi>Paul,</hi> but alſo all the Churches of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> gave thanks, whereby its evident, they had been both of them publick Labourers amongſt the Believers in all the Churches of the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> Moreover, <hi>Paul</hi> greets the Church in their Houſe; here was the Church in their Houſe; and muſt not <hi>Priſcilla</hi> ſpeak in her own Houſe? Muſt not ſhe labour there? Muſt not ſhe Pray and Propheſie there, and teach good things there? Muſt ſhe not expound the Way of God more perfectly in her own Houſe where the Church is? Is ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to Speak or Teach good things? there doth not <hi>Paul</hi> will
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101359:6"/>that Prayer be made every where; where then muſt this good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Paul</hi>'s helper in Chriſt pray, if not in her own houſe? If ſhe may and ought to pray every where then in the Church? In her houſe ſhe is not commanded Silence by <hi>Paul.</hi> Again, you may read in <hi>Acts.</hi> 21.8, 9. that <hi>Philip</hi> the Evangeliſt, one of the ſeven, had four Daughters Virgins, that did Propheſie; and <hi>Paul</hi> gave di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections how, and in what manner Women ſhall Pray and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, as may be read, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. where he ſaith, <hi>Now I pray you Brethren, that you remember me in all things, and keep the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, as I delivered them unto you, every man Praying and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying, having his Head covered, diſhonoureth his Head; but every Woman that Prayeth or Prophecyeth with her Head uncovered, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth her Head: for that is all one as if ſhe were ſhaven,</hi> &amp;c. Now he, even <hi>Paul,</hi> that gives this direction, hath adviſed to deſire after Spiritual Gifts, but rather to Propheſie; for Propheſie ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the Edification of the Church, and the Apoſtles travel and labour was, that the Church might be edified by Prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Church: So its clear he did not forbid the Female that had the Spirit of <hi>propheſie</hi> to ſpeak in the Church, to <hi>propheſie</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> in the Church; nay, he hath given directions how they ſhould demean themſelves when they <hi>pray</hi> and <hi>propheſie,</hi> and ſaith he, <hi>You may all ſpeak one by one</hi> (mark, all) <hi>that all may learn, and may be edified:</hi> God that hath poured out his Spirit is not to be limited in the Male nor Female; theſe four Daughters of <hi>Philip</hi>'s <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith did Propheſie, God had poured out his Spirit upon them for that end, that they might edifie the Church, that it might be builded up and eſtabliſhed in the moſt precious Faith of Jeſus Chriſt; ſuch Women as were thus endued, laboured in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel as well as the Men, as may be read in <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.3. <hi>And I entreat thee alſo, true yoke-Fellow, help thoſe Women which Laboured with me in the Goſpel, with</hi> Clement <hi>alſo, and with other my fellow-Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, whoſe names are in the Book of Life.</hi> Now <hi>Paul</hi> bid help the Women Labourers in and Publiſhers of the Goſpel, and not forbid them to ſpeak nor publiſh the Goſpel in the Church, for their names were written in the Book of Life, they were come to Chriſt, by him they had Life, he had poured out of his Spirit upon theſe Daughters and Handmaidens, and they were in his name, by his Power and Spirit to Propheſie, to Preach and Teach in the Church, to Labour with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Clement</hi> in the Goſpel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; yea, <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo far from forbidding, that he entreats his yoke-fellow to help them; yea, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101359:7"/>them to be Teachers of good things, as may be ſeen in <hi>Titus</hi> 2. <hi>But ſpeak thou the things</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus) which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſound Doctrine, that the aged Men may be Sober, Grave, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, ſound in Faith, in Charity, in Patience: The aged VVomen likewiſe, that they be in Behaviour as becometh Holineſs, not falſe Accuſers, not given to much VVine, Teachers</hi> (mark, Teachers) <hi>of good things, that they may Teach the young VVomen,</hi> (obſerve, Teach the young Women) <hi>to be Sober, love their Husbands, to love their Children; to be Diſcreet, Chaſte, keepers at Home, Good, Obedient to their Husbands, that the VVord of God be not Blaſphem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c. Here is good Women Teachers, this is bleſſed Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſuch Teachers are not forbidden to ſpeak in the Church, ſuch have Author<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from Chriſt and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to be Teachers of good things amongſt them, with whom they Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregate and Meet, for how ſhall they Teach them with whom they do not meet? and where two or three are gathered in the Name and Fear of Chriſt, there is he preſent, there is his Church met together, though but two or three, and Females; here they may, yea, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let the Elder be Teachers of good things to the Younger, ſuch as are learned in the School of Chriſt, have received the Spirit of Chriſt, the Spirit of Truth, that leads into all Truth, and are led thereby, acted thereby; the Spirit ſpeaking in them, may inſtruct others, teach others good things when they are gathered and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregated together, yea, in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, <hi>Paul</hi> commends <hi>Phebe</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> as may be read in <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.1. And again, makes mention of her in the Concluſion, as followeth, <hi>I commend</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>unto you</hi> Phebe <hi>our Siſter, which is a Servant of the Church, which is at</hi> Cenchrea, written to the <hi>Romans</hi> from <hi>Corinth,</hi> and ſent by <hi>Phebe Servant of the Church at</hi> Cenchrea; here <hi>Paul</hi> calls <hi>Phebe</hi> our Siſter and Servant (that is Miniſter) of the Church at <hi>Cenchrea,</hi> for a Miniſter is a Servant: So here all may ſee how <hi>Paul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends her to the <hi>Romans,</hi> as a Miniſter of the Church, and bids receive her in the Lord, as becometh Saints, and to aſſiſt her, not one Word of forbidding her to Speak and Miniſter; no, no, ſuch as laboured with him in the Goſpel was his fellow-Helpers therein, his Siſters in the Lord, and Companions in his Work and Miniſtry; yea, God Almighty through Chriſt had poured his Spirit upon them all, Sons and Daughters, Servants and Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids, they are all therefore to Propheſie, Pray, Preach and Teach as the Spirit moves, leads, inſtructs and gives utterance;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101359:7"/>all is to wait upon God to be filled with the Spirit, as <hi>Paul</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects the <hi>Epheſians, Epheſ.</hi> 5.18. <hi>Be not Drunk with Wine,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>wherein is Exceſs, but be filled with the Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he adviſeth not to grieve the Spirit, as may be read in <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30. <hi>And grieve not the holy Spirit of God, by which you are ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Day of Redemption;</hi> neither is this Spirit to be quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor Prophecying diſpiſed, as may be read in 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.19, 20. <hi>Quench not the Spirit, deſpiſe not Prophecying;</hi> now to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to ſpeak, or command ſilence where God hath poured out his Spirit upon Daughters and Handmaids, is to grieve the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to quench the Spirit, to deſpiſe Prophecying, which <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth the <hi>Epheſians</hi> and <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> not to do, but to be filled with the Spirit, to deſire ſpiritual Gifts, and rather to Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and gives the Reaſon, becauſe ſaith he, <hi>It tends to Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now by what's above written, its cleared by Scripture Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, that <hi>Paul</hi> did not forbid Women, filled with the holy Spirit, to Speak and Miniſter in the Church; ſo thoſe that uſe <hi>Paul's</hi> Words againſt ſuch Womens Speaking or Prophecying in the Church, are ignorant of the Spirit that ſpoke in <hi>Paul,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned by the ſame, knows not the meaning, myſtery or inward ſence thereof, but either takes it too Literally, or elſe as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> well obſerves, in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Even,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as our beloved Brother</hi> Paul, <hi>alſo according to the Wiſdom given unto him; as alſo in all his Epiſtles, Speaking in them of theſe things, in which are ſome things hard to be underſtood, which they that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and unſtable, wreſt, as they do alſo the other Scriptures unto their own Deſtruction:</hi> Now its ſuch as are unlearned by the Spirit of Truth, that leads into all Truth, from which Spirit the holy Scriptures were given forth, that wreſts them, for its not by any other Learning that the heavenly Myſtery in holy Writings of the Prophets and Propheteſſes, Apoſtles and holy Women can be underſtood or known, its not all the natural nor acquired Learning that may be got, that can do it, its the Inſpiration of the Almighty that gives this Knowledge and Underſtanding, its this Spirit that ſearcheth out all things, yea, the deep things of God; none can rightly read or underſtand the holy Book, but ſuch as are come to the holy Spirit according to meaſure, by which holy Men were moved to give forth, and write the ſame, that's the only Key, who wants the ſame are the unlearned and unſtable,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101359:8"/>though outwardly never ſo profoundly Learned, and its they that wreſts the Scripture, as aforeſaid, its ſuch that knows not the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of that antient and bleſſed Promiſe of the Everlaſting God, in Pouring out of his Spirit upon Sons and Daughters, Servants and Handmaidens, ſuch forbids both Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, yea, all beſides themſelves to Speak, Preach or Propheſie in the Church, they are not of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s mind, for he wiſhed all the Lords People, Prophets; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>You may all Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie one by one, and if any thing be revealed to another that ſits by, let the firſt hold his Peace;</hi> but now none muſt Speak but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, neither Son nor Daughter, neither Servant nor Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, although God hath poured his Spirit upon them, and ſaid <hi>They ſhall Propheſie:</hi> Yet notwithſtanding, ſuch as are made Miniſters by Men; Miniſters of the Letter, but ignorant of the Spirit, for the love they have to the Gain of their Miniſtry, yea, for filthy Lucer ſake they forbid all, both Men and Women be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides themſelves; and furthermore, if any that ſits by have any thing revealed, and do Speak, he or ſhe have been quickly hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out, and often either Beaten, Stockt or caſt into Priſon for three Months (by a Law made formerly to guard the Prieſts of that time) as a Diſturber: And thus while they talk of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt, Moſes, Paul</hi> and the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> they are acting quite contrary, like the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old, who in Words pretended love to <hi>God, Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> and their Writings, and to be waiting for the coming of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> yet when he came, they knew him not, received him not, though <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets were by them read every Sabboth-day, that teſtified of him, and they no doubt thought themſelves pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found in the knowledge of them; yet as before ſaid, they did not know him, nor receive him, but crucified him as the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Malefactors, and the reaſon of their Ignorance is rendred, the Vail was over their Hearts, they knew not the meaning of the Spirit that ſpoke in the Prophets that teſtified of the coming of the Juſt One; none that's ignorant of the meaning of that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that ſpoke in and through <hi>Paul,</hi> can underſtand his Writings, but either takes them too Literally, or elſe wreſts them as before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; for whoever draws that Concluſion from <hi>Paul</hi>'s words in the Text before cited, that all Females are prohibited to Speak, Teach, Preach, Pray or Propheſie in the Church or Gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God's people, do make <hi>Paul</hi> not only to contradict God
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101359:8"/>Almighty, and the Practice of many Godly Women before ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but alſo himſelf and his own Teſtimony: for firſt, God hath ſaid, <hi>They ſhall Propheſie,</hi> Chriſt hath commanded <hi>Mary,</hi> and the other before-mentioned holy Women to preach his Reſurrection in the Church to the eleven Apoſtles, and the reſt, and they did it; and we read not that any of the eleven, or the reſt of the Church then met together, did forbid them: Moreover, <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf bids help thoſe Women that laboured in the Goſpel, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends <hi>Phebe</hi> as a Servant, which is a Miniſter of the Church at <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nchera;</hi> he hath given directions alſo how the Women are to demean themſelves when they Pray or Propheſie, and ſaith he, <hi>You may all Speak or Propheſie one by one:</hi> All that have the Spirit poured forth upon them, may ſpeak as the Spirit moves and gives utterance.</p>
            <p>But it may be further objected, <hi>That if it be thus, that they may Speak and Propheſie, who have the Spirit poured forth upon them, who then are they that</hi> Paul <hi>prohibits or permits not to Speak in the Church?</hi> 1 Cor. 14.34. <hi>and</hi> 1 Tim. 2.11, 12. <hi>where he ſaith firſt to the</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, <hi>Let your Women keep ſilence in the Church; for its not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto them to ſpeak, but they are commanded to be under Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as ſaith the Law; and if they will learn any thing, let them ask their Husbands at home, for it is a ſhame for a Woman to ſpeak in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let all ſeriouſly weigh the Words of the Text; for if the Words muſt be taken in the Literal ſence, the Woman is not only prohibited ſpeaking, but learning in the Church; for its ſaid, <hi>If the Woman will learn any thing, let her ask her Husband at home.</hi> And if ſo, it doth not only contradict what God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hath ſaid ſhall be, and what holy Women have practiſed, as before clearly is demonſtrated, but alſo <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf in the very ſame Chapter, verſ. 30, 31. where he ſaith, <hi>If any thing be revealed to another that ſitteth by, let the firſt hold his Peace, for you may all</hi> (mark, all) <hi>Propheſie one by one, that all may learn,</hi> (mark) all may learn, <hi>and all be comforted;</hi> Furthermore, by the Text, Womens Teaching or Prophecying is not prohibited, but to ſpeak, which ſpeaking muſt by the Words before related, be underſtood to be Queſtions tending to <hi>ſtrife</hi> &amp; the <hi>diſturbance</hi> of the Church, wherefore its ſaid, <hi>Let her ask her Husband at home:</hi> And ſuch Speaking or Queſtions tendeth not to Edification &amp; Comfort, but Diſturbance and Contention, of which there is no cuſtom in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101359:9"/>Churches of Chriſt: And further, to manifeſt that this was <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſence, hear what he ſaith to the ſame <hi>Corinthians</hi> in Chap. 11. <hi>Now in this that I declare unto you I praiſe you not, that you come together not for the better, but for the worſe; for firſt of all when you come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Church, I hear that there be Diviſions among you, and I partly believe it.</hi> Now its ſuch ſpeaking as tendeth to Diviſion and Contention, that's for the worſe, and not for the better in the Church, that's forbidden, but teaching good things, Praying or Prophecying, is for the better, praiſe-worthy, tends to Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and Comfort, and hath no tendance to Strife or Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neither can any reaſon be rendred that ſuch Women thus Teaching, Praying or Prophecying ſhould be refered to learn of their outward Husbands at home; beſides, many have none: Further, <hi>Paul</hi> in his ſecond Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy</hi> very clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares what manner of Speaking, and the Spkeaers which are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden in the Church, hear what he ſaith, <hi>Of theſe things put them in remembrance, charging them before the Lord, that they ſtrive not about Words to no profit, but to the ſubverting of the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: Shun prophane and vain Bablings, for they will encreaſe unto more <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs, and their Words will eat as doth a Canker: but fooliſh and unlearned Queſtions avoid, knowing that they gender. Strife, having a Form of Godlineſs, but denying the Power thereof, from ſuch turn away; for of this ſort are they which creep into Houſes, and lead captive ſilly Women, loaden with Sins, led away with divers Luſts, ever learning, and never able to come to the Knowledge of the Truth:</hi> Here are the Women deſcribed that are not permitted to ſpeak in the Church; alſo the Speaking, the vain Babling and unlearned Queſtions that grenders Strife, from them that have a form of Godlineſs, but deny the Power, ſuch Speakers and ſpeaking is not permitted in the Church; this tends not to Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and Comfort, and teaching good things, and Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying doth, that all may do in the Church that hath the Spirit poured upon them. But ſuch Queſtions are not proper or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient in the Church, they uſurp Authority that are found in the Practice thereof; there's no ſuch Order or Cuſtom in the Churches of Chriſt, for what's there done, is to be to Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if Women that are thus idle, buſie-Bodies and Diſorderly ſhall propoſe, ask, or ſpeak any ſuch things or Queſtions, ought not to do it in the Church, they are not permitted there, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let them ask their Husbands, or others at home, ſuch are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101359:9"/>unlearned, not come to the knowledge of the Truth that ſets Free, but in the Sin and Bondage, in the Tranſgreſſion and Fall from God, where the Subjection is to be kept under, and the Husband is to rule over, as ſaith the Law; <hi>Its a Shame for ſuch to Speak in the Church,</hi> ſuch are not Witneſſes of the Reſtoration by Chriſt, in whom Male and Female are all one, and he in both may Speak in his Church, Propheſie in his Church to Edification and Comfort, that all may Learn, and that all may be Edified and Comforted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As to the Words of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> which are as followeth, <hi>viz. But I ſuffer not a Woman to Teach nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over the Man, but to be in Silence.</hi> Here is not one word of Teaching in the Church, but hath only relation to ſuch as would uſurp Authority over the Man, which <hi>Paul</hi> permits not, ſuffers not, to teach in that Uſurpation, but ſuch as are taught by the Spirit he permits and commands to teach others good things, to Love and Obey their Husbands, not to uſurp Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over them; for all that comes to learn of Chriſt and his good Spirit, they learn Meekneſs, Humility and lowlineſs of Mind, and ſuch know how to Honour their Husbands, Obey their Husbands, and are thereby preſerved out of the Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though God by his Spirit, that's not to be limited, may make them Inſtrumental to Inſtruct their Husbands, as he did by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> her Husband was commanded of God to Obey and Anſwer what ſhe Taught or Inſtructed him in, yet the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>She called</hi> Abraham <hi>(her Husband) Lord;</hi> here is no Uſurpation there.</p>
            <p>Wherefore its clear that <hi>Paul</hi>'s Words of not permitting or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Women to Speak, had only relation to the Unlearned, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly, the Uſurpers of Authority amongſt the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> or other Churches, ſuch as uſurped Authority over the Man, ſuch are to be ſlent, they are not permitted to Speak in the Church, they Miniſter Strife and Contention, and there's no ſuch cuſtom in the Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Further, it may very properly be queri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of all Objecters, in this wiſe, <hi>That if Women muſt Learn of their Husbands at Home, of whom then muſt they Learn that have no Husbands, if there be no other way of Learning, then muſt they be concluded in Ignorance to remain?</hi> But <hi>Philip</hi>'s four Daughters had no outward Husbands to Learn of, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>they were Virgins,</hi> yet well Learned, they did Propheſie, wherefore the prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101359:10"/>by him of not ſpeaking, belongs not to, nor hath any rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them, nor ſuch other, they may notwithſtanding Speak and Propheſie in the Church, and all others who have the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Propheſie poured out upon them, as the ſame Spirit moves and gives utterance.</p>
            <p>Now to conclude, God Almighty that's greater then all, hath ſaid, <hi>They ſhall Propheſie;</hi> and Daughters and Handmaids have Propheſied, both in time of the Law and Goſpel Diſpenſation in the Churches or Congregation, <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Lord and Law-giver hath Commanded and Commiſſioned Women to Teach or Preach or Propheſie in the Church, as before is clearly demonſtrated, and they obeyed and practiced; moreover <hi>Paul</hi> hath commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Daughters and Handmaids to the Churches, Commanded to receive and aſſiſt them, and to help thoſe Women that laboured with him in the Goſpel, they did Propheſie, ſaith he: Therefore let all Gain-ſayers and Contradictors of God Alimighty, of Chriſt Jeſus the Lord and Law-giver, and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> ceaſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from and ſtop their Mouths for ever, and let the Unlearned and Unſtable, ceaſe to pervert or wreſt the Holy Scriptures, for ſuch know not the meaning of the Spirit that ſpoke in the Prophets and Apoſtles, Holy Men and Women that have given out the Holy Scriptures by Inſpiration of God, and is profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction, for Inſtruction in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and are able to make wiſe unto Salvation through Faith, which is in Chriſt Jeſus, that the Man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good Works, Glory to God for the unſpeakable Comfort thereof, adminiſtered through the Holy Spirit.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A <hi>POSTSCRIPT</hi> of ſome Teſtimonies ſhewing, that the Apoſtles <hi>Precepts</hi> againſt Womens Speaking was not univerſal; and that Women have had a Service in the univerſal Church in ſeveral Ages.</head>
            <p>BEfore the Law was given, <hi>Miriam</hi> was given for a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.20. <hi>Mica.</hi> 6.4. And among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law of Nature (as 'tis called) the <hi>Sibyls</hi> in ſeveral Ages propheſied; <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>By the ſame Spirit of God that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did to the</hi> Jews, Decivit. dei l. 18. c. 18. And Biſhop <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagues</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101359:10"/>writes a whole Book about that matter, <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> (before Chriſt) the 9th Book.</p>
            <p>And for Womens Services under the Law, and under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, Biſhop <hi>John Bridges</hi> writes near a whole Book, <hi>Defence,</hi> &amp;c. 9th Book, where he ſhews that though <hi>Calvin</hi> was the vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt againſt Womens Teaching, of all that he had read, yet he makes his conceſſion this, <hi>That as neceſſity might require this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of</hi> Paul <hi>of the ordinary courſe, maketh no abſolute debar to all manner of Women, but that now and then ſome may ſpeak lawfully;</hi> Yea, and their Voice is requiſit, even in the moſt ſacred, publick and greateſt Aſſemblies of the Churches. The ſaid <hi>J. Bridges</hi> alſo brings the further Conceſſions of <hi>Peter Martyr, Muſculus, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorat, Aleſius, Aretius,</hi> and other emnient Teachers, all granting <hi>Paul</hi>'s precept not to be an univerſal reſtraint, bringing the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Women under the Law, as well as Goſpel times for inſtances, as <hi>Philip</hi>'s Daughters, <hi>Anna, Deborah, Hulda, Hannab.</hi> The Womans Claim, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.7, 9. <hi>Abigal</hi> the Woman of <hi>Abel,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.18. The Mother of the ſeven Sons, 2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 7. <hi>Judith.</hi> The Woman, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.27. The Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> The Woman <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.20. and <hi>Luke</hi> 8.44. The Woman of <hi>Canaan, Matth.</hi> 15.22. The Woman of <hi>Samaria, Miriam, Elizabeth, Samſon</hi>'s Mother, <hi>Judg.</hi> 13.22. The captive Maid, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.2. and others. That though they be under ſubjection, yet they may ſpeak, counſel, and teach. <hi>So Bridges</hi> ſays, <hi>Defence.</hi> lib. 1. (which I have heard was ſet out in Churches) <hi>That Extraordinary Gifts are not altogether ceaſed in the Church. Gualter</hi> an Entertainer and Adviſer of Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> Biſhops, on <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. ſays, <hi>Paul is not aſhamed to call</hi> Priſcilla <hi>his fellow-Helper, not aſhamed of a Woman at the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>whoſe Faith was ſpoken of through the World.</hi> That ſhe was the firſt named, becauſe perhaps ſhe was firſt converted, and more known, afterwards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing her Husband, &amp; they expounded the Way of the Lord to <hi>Apollos,</hi> and without doubt to many others, making their Houſe a publick Meeting-Houſe, in time of Perſecution. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Every Father and Mother in a Family ſhould play the Biſhop.</hi> So <hi>Gualter</hi> called the learned, who ſpeaks there much againſt the haughtineſs of the Clergy, deſpiſing mean helps, knowing that in Jeſus Chriſt there is neither Male nor Female. So Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> ſays (<hi>Prim. Chriſt.</hi> part. 1. c. 8.) <hi>He meets with frequent mention of</hi> Deaconeſſes <hi>in ancient Writings, as</hi> Phebe, <hi>two Maids in</hi> Pliny's <hi>Letter to the Emperor;</hi> Clem. Alex. ſtrom. l. 3.
<pb facs="tcp:101359:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Of</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> calls them <hi>She <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. W. Tindal,</hi> that famous Martyr, in his Anſwer to Sr <hi>Thomas Moor,</hi> pag. 322. and 287. ſays, <hi>In ſome caſes Women may Teach and Baptize, and Rule their Husbands too if they be beſides themſelves: Yea,</hi> ſays he, <hi>if Hiſtories be true, Women have preached ſince the opening of the New-Teſtament.</hi> And in four Hiſtorians of the ancient Church, (<hi>Socrat. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>Theod. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>Sozom. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>Niceph. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 34.) we find that a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man converted the Nation of the <hi>Iberes,</hi> who firſt converted the King, then he preached to the men, and ſhe and the Queen to the Women. <hi>Puffinus</hi> ſaith, he received it from <hi>Bocurius</hi> their firſt Ruler. And even in declining and corrupter times, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made in Hiſtories, what liberty Women had in ſome Councils. As in <hi>Wilfrid (Samms Brit.)</hi> a chief Biſhops time, when he would excommunicate the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Northern Engliſh,</hi> becauſe they would not receive the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Rites, <hi>Hilda</hi> Abbeſs of <hi>Whitby</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> withſtood him, <hi>Illyricus teſt. verit.</hi> And alſo in his time in a Council at <hi>Baconkeld,</hi> five <hi>Kentiſh</hi> Abeſſes were not only preſent, but ſubſcribed their Names above all <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, <hi>G. G. Brit. ch. hiſt. Cent.</hi> 7. And <hi>Illyricus</hi> mentions another <hi>Engliſh</hi> Abbeſs that wrote to the Pope in defence of Ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons. And <hi>Heldegardis</hi> ſhe inſtructed the Pope in his Life, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whom <hi>Ja. Max<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell</hi> in his Book of Propheſies (dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to K. <hi>James</hi>'s Biſhops) produces, with many other Women. And in the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> it was confeſſed, <hi>That the Service of women in the Church was degenerated,</hi> Hiſt. Counc. of Trent. l. 2. In the year 1414. <hi>Joan VVhite</hi> taught &amp; ſpread her <hi>husbands doctrine, J. Fox</hi> Martyr. And Dr. <hi>Rol. Taylor</hi> ſpeaks of Womens Services. In the laſt Age a Woman was principal Ordinary in the Church hers; and in her time there remained Permiſſion for Women to Baptize, as well as in her Siſters time <hi>(Conference at Hampton-Court)</hi> and I find nothing, but there doth yet. and then why not to Preach? For many therein are permitted to Preach, yet not to Baptize? And tis a Rule, that they that may do the greater may do the leſſer. However, they are not only permitted, but commanded in the <hi>Liturgies Rubrick,</hi> to ſpeak in the repetition of the <hi>Creed, Reſponſes, Pſalms,</hi> &amp;c. if they be of the Congregation, though not Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eiſes. For all are not Prophets, <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, whoſe reſtraint therefore is not univerſal (confeſſed by Judgment and Practice) but on occaſion of Abuſe, as <hi>Jerom</hi> ſays, and <hi>Calvin</hi> too.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>RICHARD RICHARDSON.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
